Winchester-Moore Family papers, Inclusive: circa 1855-1972, undated, Bulk: 1922-1937, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Winchester-Moore Family papers
Inclusive: circa 1855-1972, undated, Bulk: 1922-1937, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
460
Winchester, R.G.
1.3 document boxes, 1 oversize folder
The Winchester-Moore Family papers are focused on the life of Robert G. Winchester, but also include items related to his mother’s family, the Moores. The collection includes clippings, photographs, event invitations and announcements, and several other items of interest from throughout the family.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Robert Glenn Winchester and his twin brother, William Penn Winchester, were born 1905 December 18 just outside Waco, Texas, in what is now Robinson. Their parents were Mary Katherine Moore Winchester, originally of Atlanta, Georgia, and Robert Stevenson Winchester, born in Union County, North Carolina. R. S. Winchester worked for the railroad which relocated his family to Texas, spending time in Waco and Yoakum. The Winchester’s also had a younger brother, Albert.
R. G. Winchester was a Waco High School (1923) and Baylor University (1927) graduate. In 1955 he helped his mother fund a newspaper reading room in the Baylor Libraries to honor his late twin brother, William Winchester, who died in a bus-train accident while attending Baylor. In 1971, Winchester authored a book, James Pinckney Henderson: Texas’ First Governor; this was the first biography written about Pinckney.
Robert G. Winchester was a longtime teacher and Principal at Yoakum High School in Yoakum, Texas. Shortly before his death in 1980 a senior scholarship was created in his honor, “The Robert G. Winchester Outstanding Citizen Award.” Winchester died 1980 August 19 and is interred at Oakwood Cemetery in Waco, Texas.
Scope and Content
The General series documents regular activities of the Winchester-Moore Family. Graduation announcements, newspapers and clippings, correspondence, and printed materials are available. Certificates and awards are also present, including an honorary varsity letter certificate presented to William Winchester following his death.
The Baylor University series accounts for several members of the Moore and Winchester families who attended Baylor University. Notably, William P. Winchester was a student in 1927 and lost his life in a tragic bus-train accident. Several items from his involvement as a student athlete are represented as well as a folder titled “Immortal Ten” which documents the tragedy. Other general items and clippings are also present.
The Waco Shakespeare Club series documents the activities and interests of Mrs. Mary Katherine Moore Winchester as part of the club. She served as President from 1941-1943 for which she was given a book of daily Shakespeare quotations, attended the annual conference of Women’s Clubs, and traveled to Stratford-upon-Avon where she collected several art prints of the area. Three card games inspired by the works of Shakespeare are also included.
Photographs document several generations of the Winchester-Moore family. Weddings, graduations, individual portraits, and extended family photographs are present. Also represented are several aunts, uncles, and cousins, including Henry Price (Nora Winchester’s husband) who served as a state legislator in North Carolina. Also included are photographs taken by noted Waco photographer Fred Gildersleeve.
Arrangement
A previous inventory and partial finding aid existed for this collection; it was arranged in two series but did not account for several materials received later. Current arrangement includes these materials and is in four series: I. General, II. Baylor University, III. Waco Shakespeare Club, IV. Photographs.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 460. Acquired 1973-02-01
Related Resources
Related references
“Districts, Regions, Centers, With Respective Committees.” Interscholastic Leaguer 20, no. 5 (1937). Accessed 2019 July 26.
Find A Grave, Inc. “Robert G. Winchester.” Memorial #23625716. Databases. Accessed 2019 July 26.
“Memorial Room Will Honor Baylor Cager Who Died In Crash.” Lubbock Morning Avalanche (Lubbock, TX), 1955 March 27. Accessed 2019 July 26.
Yoakum Sesquicentennial/Centennial Book Committee. Yoakum Community: The First Hundred Years 1887-1987. Dallas, Texas: Curtis Media Corporation, 1988.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Gildersleeve, Fred A., 1881?-1958.
Subjects (Organizations)
Waco Shakespeare Club (Waco, Tex.)
Subjects
Announcements.; Baylor University.; Certificates.; College students -- Texas -- Death -- History -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Football -- Texas.; Genealogy.; Prints.; Railroad accidents -- Texas -- Round Rock -- History -- 20th century.; Women -- Texas -- Waco -- Societies and clubs.
Genres
Card games.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Newspapers.; Photographs.
- General, 1911-1977; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The General series, dated 1911-1972, includes clippings, programs and announcements, correspondence, and several oversize newspaper items. Also included are certificates, letters of recommendation, and printed materials. The series is arranged alphabetically and in good condition.
  - Clippings, 1927-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1924-1943 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Commencement, 1911-1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, circa 1912-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Daily Lariat, 1924-1972 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - High School Football, 1922-1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Printed Material, 1918-1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Robert G. Winchester Teacher Employment, 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Robert G. and William P. Winchester Tests and Transcripts (Restricted), 1923-1930 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - William P. Winchester, 1923-1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - William P. Winchester Diploma, 1923 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 1)
- Baylor University, 1924-1945, undated; 2
  The Baylor University series, 1924-1945, includes general university related clippings as well as those related to athletics and the “Immortal Ten.” Other items include ticket stubs, rosters, and general memorabilia. The series is arranged alphabetically and in good condition.
  - Clippings: Athletics, 1924, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clippings: General, 1924, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings: Immortal Ten, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General, 1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General: Athletics, 1924-1927 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letterman’s Certificate, 1927 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 1)
- Waco Shakespeare Club, 1923-1949, undated; 3
  The Waco Shakespeare Club series, dated 1923-1949, includes several Shakespeare inspired card games, art prints from a trip to Stratford-on-Avon, and club by-laws. Also included are event programs, personal writings, and a book of quotations. Items are arranged alphabetically and in average to good condition.
  - Art Prints, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Card Games, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - General, 1923-1949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Photographs, circa 1885-1972, undated; 4
  The Photographs series, dated 1855-1966, includes several generations from the Moore and Winchester families. Weddings, graduations, accomplishments, individual and family portraits are included. The series is arranged alphabetically and is in good condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Football Teams, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Moore Family, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Moore Family, circa 1885-1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Annie (Moore) Palmer, 1910-1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - (Winchester) Price Family, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Winchester Family (1 of 2), 1905- circa 1933 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Winchester Family (2 of 2), 1905- circa 1933 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Robert G. Winchester, 1924-1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - William P. Winchester, 1922-1935 (Box 2, Folder 5)